{"tossups": [{"question": "A rebellion against this man occurred because Emma's marriage to Ralph de Ga\u00ebl was not sanctioned. That revolt against this man is known as the Revolt of the Earls. This man ordered allegiance in the Salisbury Oath, and at the southern end of the London Bridge, this man fought Ansgar [[ON-sgar]] the Staller and burned Southwark [[SUH-therk]]. This man built the White Tower, created the New Forest for royal hunting, and commissioned the Domesday [[DOOMS-day]] Book for listing landholdings. For ten points, name this Norman King who won at Hastings.", "answer": "<b><u>William the Conqueror</u></b> (accept <b><u>William I</u></b>; accept <b><u>William the Bastard</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In 2010, various artists proclaimed \"[Do this action] Day\" after Episode 201 of South Park was censored on Comedy Central. In 2015, Elton Simpson, along with an accomplice, attacked the Curtis Culwell Center, because the American Freedom Defense Initiative, or AFDI, did this. The AFDI had held the event because earlier that year, militants slaughtered artists at <em>Charlie Hebdo</em> who had done, for ten points, what <em>haram</em> action relating to the last prophet of Islam?", "answer": "<b><u>Depict</u></b>ing <b><u>Muhammad</u></b> (prompt on <b><u>icon</u></b>ography; accept descriptive answers related to creating images of <b><u>Muhammad</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A man in this position, Newton Baker, rejected David Lloyd George\u2019s advice on how to mobilize a nation. Robert Todd Lincoln served in this position during the James Garfield and Chester Arthur administrations, putting down the Cincinnati Riots of 1884. Andrew Johnson violated the Tenure of Office Act by sacking a man in this position, leading to his impeachment. For ten points, name this Cabinet position held by Jefferson Davis and Edwin Stanton, now known as the Secretary of Defense.", "answer": "United States <b><u>Secretary</u></b> of <b><u>War</u></b> (do not accept or prompt on \"Secretary of Defense\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "As a rookie, this Hall-of-Famer batted .174 [[One seventy-four]] for Kansas City. Five years later, this man won his first of three World Series in a row and was voted league MVP the following year. A teammate described this flamboyant player saying, \"There isn't enough mustard in the whole world to cover that hotdog.\" When this man retired in 1987, his 563 career home runs ranked him sixth all-time. Holding the World Series records for most runs and most homers in a single series, for ten points, who is this slugger, nicknamed \u201cMr. October\"?", "answer": "Reggie <b><u>Jackson</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A battle for power in this country was fought between The Four Musketeers and the Promoters. Phibun [[PEE-BOON]], a member of the Khana Ratsadon People's party, led this country's Rebellion of 18 Corpses. The Black May protests in this country occurred after the NPKC launched a coup. Since 1932, this country has had twenty constitutions, and protestors in this country's Thammasat [[TAH-meh-sawt]] University were attacked in 1973. Ruled by the House of Chakri and kings named Rama, for ten points, name this country once called Siam.", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>Thailand</u></b> (accept <b><u>Siam</u></b> before \"Black May\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The first provisional governor of this state, Wyandot [[WHY-an-dot]] leader William Walker, was unrecognized by the federal government. The first official governor of this state, David Butler, was impeached, and another governor, Silas Holcomb, ran on a combined Democratic/Populist ticket. William Jennings Bryan's brother, Charles Wayland, served as governor of this state, whose first female governor was Kay Orr. In 2015, Pete Ricketts became governor of, for ten points, what state which is governed from Lincoln?", "answer": "<b><u>Nebraska</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This proto-state intentionally opened the Nuaimiya Dam near Fallujah to deprive the Shia majority population of water. Late 2016 campaigns led to the loss of this organization\u2019s stronghold of Mosul and its capital of Raqqa [[ROK-ah]]. Donald Trump approved of Operation Kayla Mueller, which killed this leader\u2019s \u201cCaliph\u201d Abu Bakr Al-Baghdadi. For ten points, name this terrorist state which controlled portions of Iraq and Syria.", "answer": "<b><u>Islamic State of Iraq and the Levant</u></b> (accept <b><u>ISIL</u></b>; accept <b><u>Islamic State of Iraq</u></b> <b><u>and Syria</u></b>; accept <b><u>ISIS</u></b>; prompt on \"Islamic State\"; accept <b><u>Daesh</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "Shostakovich's Opus 77 is a notable concerto for this instrument in A-minor. The Spanish virtuoso Pablo de Sarasate [[SAR-ah-SAH-tay]] refused to play this instrument for the debut of Brahms's D-major concerto for this instrument due to the length of the oboe section. Vivaldi's <em>Four Seasons</em> are concertos for this instrument, versions of which, including the \"Molitor\" and the \"Lady Blunt,\" were manufactured by Antonio Stradivari. For ten points, name this string instrument played with a bow, which has a higher pitch than a cello or viola.", "answer": "<b><u>Violin</u></b> (or <b><u>fiddle</u></b>; do not accept or prompt on \"viola\")", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "The most easterly of these cities, known as <em>eskhata</em>, was founded in the Fergana Valley as a way to maintain contact with the Sogdians. Another of these cities, partially named for a horse, served as a settlement for Iranian and Greek veterans. Another city with this name was the site of the <em>Pharos</em> which was built by the Ptolemies. For ten points, give this shared name of twenty cities founded by Alexander the Great, the most notable containing an extensive library.", "answer": "<b><u>Alexandria</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "David Koch [[KOHK]] ran on this party\u2019s ticket in the Election of 1980, being the only ticket to platform equality for LGBT individuals in America. It\u2019s not the Republican Party, but one faithless elector voted for a member of this party named Ron Paul in the Election of 2016. The response \u201cWhat is Aleppo?\u201d was said by a presidential candidate from this party, Gary Johnson. For ten points, name this U.S. party which supports <em>Laissez-faire</em> economics and hands-off government.", "answer": "<b><u>Libertarian</u></b> Party (prompt on \"LP\")", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This program was allegorized as Fascism by Kurt Weill [[VILE]] and Maxwell Anderson in <em>Knickerbocker Holiday</em>. Democrat Jouett Shouse [[JO-ett SHOUSS]] opposed this program which was attacked by the American Liberty League, including Empire State Building creator John J. Raskob and the du Pont brothers. This program created the FDIC and allowed for farmers to have electricity in the Rural Electrification Act. The TVA was created under, for ten points, what set of FDR-created programs which aided Americans in the Great Depression?", "answer": "The <b><u>New Deal</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This scientist's home was the Down House, whose grounds contain a \"sandwalk\" which this scientist called his \"thinking path.\" On one journey to South America, this scientist wrote that a native species of fox \"would undermine the stability of species.\" This scientist's observations of tortoises helped him formulate his idea that species change over time. This scientist recorded his travels in the book <em>The Voyage of the Beagle</em>. For ten points, name this English scientist, who outlined his theory of natural selection in <em>On the Origin of</em> <em>Species</em>.", "answer": "Charles <b><u>Darwin</u></b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Anthropology"}, {}, {"question": "In 1305, a queen of Navarre with this first name supposedly died from witchcraft performed by the Bishop of Troyes [[TWAH]]. Many historical female aristocrats held this name, including \"of Lancaster\" and \"of the Tower.\" A Medieval chronicle written by Jean de Mailly [[mai-YEE]] tells of a female Pope by this name, now widely considered to be fictional. For ten points, give this name commonly associated with a French warrior saint who broke the English and Burgundian siege of Orl\u00e9ans during the Hundred Years' War.", "answer": "<b><u>Joan</u></b> (accept <b><u>Joan</u></b> I of Navarre; accept <b><u>Joan</u></b> of Lancaster; accept <b><u>Joan</u></b> of the Tower; accept Pope <b><u>Joan</u></b>; accept <b><u>Joan</u></b> of Arc)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "At McGill, this man won several Wicksteed medals for gymnastics. Luther Gullick may have ordered this man to create a game, but Lambert Will's family disputes that. Legendary coach \"Phog\" Allen was himself coached by this man, who worked to get African-Americans the right to use university swimming pools. Neither dribbling nor free throws were part of this man's original rules. This Canadian invented a sport at the YMCA in Springfield, Massachusetts. For ten points, name this creator of the game of basketball.", "answer": "James <b><u>Naismith</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "After the 1960 Sharpeville massacre, this organization established the uMkhonto we Sizwe [[oom-KOHN-toh weh SEEZ-weh]], or \"Spear of the Nation.\" The Spear of the Nation was founded by a man who gave his \u201cI Am Prepared to Die\u201d speech at the Rivonia Trial, which sent members of this organization to a prison on Robben Island. This organization elected Cyril Ramaphosa as president in 2017, the year before he was also elected president of South Africa. For ten points, name this South African political party once led by Nelson Mandela.", "answer": "<b><u>African National Congress</u></b> (accept <b><u>ANC</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "During this event, Gail Halvorsen popularized the mass distribution of candy to children in Operation Little Vittles. SPD party member Ernst Reuter gave a speech beside the ruined Reichstag urging the people of America, England, and France to not abandon his city during this event. At the height of this event, an Allied aircraft reached its target with supplies every thirty seconds. For ten points, name this event in which the Soviets attempted to stop supply lines to the West German capital, the first major crisis of the Cold War.", "answer": "<b><u>Berlin Blockade</u></b> (accept <b><u>Berlin Airlift</u></b>; or Berliner <em><b><u>Luftbr\u00fccke</u></b></em>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "While traveling on this body of water, one god turned into a blazing disk which blinded an enemy army. Ancient people believed this body of water was controlled from beneath Elephantine Island. This body of water was ruled by gods such as Khnum and the androgynous potbellied deity Hapi. The flooding of this body of water was critical to regional agriculture and was believed to be controlled by the Pharaoh. For ten points, name this river which features prominently in Egyptian mythology.", "answer": "<b><u>Nile</u></b> River", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "In the <em>Federal Baseball Club</em> case, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Jr. stated that this law did not apply to Major League Baseball. It has been argued that this law\u2019s namesake used it to lessen the blow of his ally William McKinley\u2019s harsh tariff passed three months later. This law, strengthened by a 1914 act sponsored by Alabama Representative Henry D. Clayton, was ironically often used to break up labor unions in the late 19th century. For ten points, name this 1890 law intended to limit monopolies.", "answer": "<b><u>Sherman Antitrust</u></b> Act of 1890", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Daughter of Powhatan, also named Rebecca Rolfe and Matoaka", "answer": "<b><u>Pocahontas</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Last member of the Patuxet who taught farming to the Pilgrims in New England", "answer": "<b><u>Squanto</u></b> (accept <b><u>Tisquantum</u></b>)   Creator of the Cherokee Syllabary who was also known as George Guess (3)  ANSWER: <b><u>Sequoyah</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Apache medicine man who broke out of a reservation and was exiled to Florida", "answer": "<b><u>Geronimo</u></b> (accept <b><u>Goyaale</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Metis leader and founder of Manitoba who led the Red River Rebellion", "answer": "Louis <b><u>Riel</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Mohawk leader who founded the Iroquois with Deganawidah", "answer": "<b><u>Hiawatha</u></b> (or <b><u>Ayenwathaaa</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Yamacraw Creek chief who granted land to James Oglethorpe in Georgia", "answer": "<b><u>Tomochichi</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Last member of the Californian Yahi people whose real name is unknown", "answer": "<b><u>Ishi</u></b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Psychology"}, {"question": "Destructive global conflict which began as a result of the assassination", "answer": "<b><u>World War One</u></b> (or <b><u>First World War</u></b>; accept The <b><u>Great War</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Dual monarchy Franz Ferdinand helped lead as Archduke", "answer": "<b><u>Austria-Hungary</u></b> (or <b><u>Austro-Hungarian</u></b> Empire or Monarchy)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Man who shot Franz Ferdinand after his driver made a wrong turn", "answer": "Gavrilo <b><u>Princip</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Serbian nationalist organization that was implicated in the assassination", "answer": "The <b><u>Black Hand</u></b> (accept <b><u>Unification or Death</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Crisis sparked by the assassination during which Russia mobilized its armed forces", "answer": "<b><u>July</u></b> Crisis", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Emperor who, despite hearing of the assassination, continued his spa vacation", "answer": "<b><u>Franz Joseph</u></b> I", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Wife of the archduke who was assassinated along with him", "answer": "<b><u>Sophie</u></b>, Duchess of Hohenberg (accept Sophie <b><u>Chotek</u></b>)   Crown Prince whose suicide in the Mayerling incident made Franz Ferdinand the (8)  heir apparent  ANSWER: <b><u>Rudolf</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Country the Han dynasty controlled from Chang'an and later Luoyang", "answer": "<b><u>China</u></b> (accept <b><u>Zhongguo</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Religion legendarily founded by Lao Tsu whose members revolted during the Han", "answer": "<b><u>Taoism</u></b> (or <b><u>Daoism</u></b>; or <b><u>Daojiao</u></b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "Rebellion led by Zhang Jiao and named for colorful headwear which weakened the dynasty", "answer": "<b><u>Yellow Turban</u></b> Rebellion (accept <b><u>Yellow Scarves</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The Han established this trade route, named for a natural fiber used to make fine cloth", "answer": "<b><u>Silk</u></b> Road", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Numbered period of civil war that followed the fall of the Han and included clashes between Cao Cao, Sun Jian, and Liu Bei", "answer": "<b><u>Three Kingdoms</u></b> (or <b><u>Sanguo Shidai</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Dynasty founded by Wang Mang which temporarily interrupted the Han.", "answer": "<b><u>Xin</u></b> [[SHIN]] Dynasty", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Pair of Vietnamese sisters who rebelled against the Han Dynasty in 40 CE.", "answer": "<b><u>Trung</u></b> Sisters (or <b><u>Trung</u></b> Trac and <b><u>Trung</u></b> Nhi)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Warlord who employed Lu Bu and seized power after deposing Liu Bian", "answer": "<b><u>Dong</u></b> Zhuo (accept either or both names; accept <b><u>Zhongying</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This country held the Nias [[NAI-ahs]] Expedition and fought two wars against</u></b> <b><u>the Kingdom of Bone. This country fought the Chinese in Montrado and aided the</u></b> <b><u>Adats in the Padri War. This country used the \"Peace Policy\" to take South Sulawesi</u></b> <b><u>[[soo-lah-WEH-see]], part of its (+)</u> Great East governorate. This country fought the Infidel War in Aceh [[AH-cheh]] on Sumatra, and after Prince Diponegoro [[dee-pah-neh-GO-roh]] began a revolt in Selarong, this country fought the Java War in (*) </b>Batavia. For ten points, name this European country which controlled Indonesia until 1949.", "answer": "The <b><u>Netherlands</u></b> (accept <b><u>Holland</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>An artist created a painting during this war depicting a politician bleeding out</u></b> <b><u>while being protected by freedman Peter Salem. Artist John Trumbull served in this</u></b> <b><u>war, later painting a scene of William Phillips and another general surrendering</u></b> <b><u>during this war. (+)</u> Emanuel Leutze [[LOIT-zuh]] painted multiple scenes of this war, including one where several figures including James (*) </b>Monroe and Nathaniel Greene traverse a half-frozen river. For ten points, name this war, the setting of <em>Washington</em> <em>Crossing the Delaware</em>.", "answer": "<b><u>Revolutionary</u></b> War (accept <b><u>American Revolution</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man fought the filibusters in the Gutierrez-Magee Expedition and was</u></b> <b><u>cited for bravery after the Battle of Medina. With Guadalupe Victoria, this man signed</u></b> <b><u>the Plan of Casa Mata to oppose Emperor (*)</u> Augustine's Plan of Iguala. This man traded his highest office with the leader of the </b><em><b>puros</b></em><b>, Valentin Gomez Farias. James Austin Sylvester captured this man hiding in a marsh after the Battle of (*) </b>San Jacinto. For ten points, name this twelve-time Mexican president who lost the Mexican-American War despite his victory at the Alamo.", "answer": "Antonio L\u00f3pez de <b><u>Santa Anna</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This group was founded by William Ireland, Aaron Grosh and Oliver Kelley.</u></b> <b><u>Wisconsin passed a strict rate-fixing law based on this group's advocacy called the</u></b> <b><u>Potter Law, which stopped all railroad construction in the state. (*)</u> Certain consumers were offered goods through Montgomery Ward, which associated itself with this organization which spurned the </b><em><b>Munn v. Illinois</b></em><b> decision and created (*) </b>Rural Free Delivery. For ten points, name this fraternal agricultural organization popular after the Civil War.", "answer": "The <b><u>Grange</u></b> (accept The National <b><u>Grange</u></b> of the Order of Patrons of Husbandry)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Possibly as a result of miners finding these objects, Herodotus made the claim</u></b> <b><u>that gryphons protected gold mines in Hyperborea. The race between Othniel Charles</u></b> <b><u>Marsh and Edward Drinker Cope to collect these objects has been dubbed their (+)</u></b> <b>namesake \"war.\" Because he did not believe in extinction, Thomas Jefferson claimed that some of these objects were actually the (*) </b>remains of an unknown species of elephant. For ten points, name these preserved remains of prehistoric life studied by paleontologists.", "answer": "<b><u>Fossil</u></b>s (accept <b><u>Bone</u></b>s; accept <b><u>Skeleton</u></b>s)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>This country sent the Balmis Expedition to vaccinate millions against</u></b> <b><u>smallpox. The Duke of Olivares served a king of this nation as did Luis de Haro. This</u></b> <b><u>country took Breda in 1624, as shown in Diego (*)</u> Velazquez's </b><em><b>The Surrender of </b><b>Breda</b></em><b>, and it signed the Treaty of the Pyrenees to marry Maria Theresa to Louis XIV and end its war with (*) </b>France. The \"Planet King\" of this country patronized authors like Lope de Vega and Calderon de la Barca. For ten points, name this state whose Habsburg rulers included kings named Felipe and Carlos.", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>Spain</u></b> (accept <b><u>Spanish</u></b> Empire)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Portraits of this artist often feature a broken nose, reflecting an incident in</u></b> <b><u>which Pietro Torrigiano [[tohr-EE-jee-AH-noh]] punched him in the face. During</u></b> <b><u>Pentecost in 1972, a disturbed geologist named Laszlo Toth vandalized this artist's</u></b> <b><u>(*)</u> </b><em><b>Piet\u00e0</b></em><b>. One of this artist's paintings was the subject of the \"fig leaf\" campaign. Due to a mistranslation of the word for \"halo,\" this artist created a sculpture of (*) </b>Moses with two horns. For ten points, name this Italian renaissance artist, who painted <em>The Last</em> <em>Judgement</em> and the Sistine Chapel ceiling.", "answer": "<b><u>Michelangelo</u></b> Buonarroti (accept <b><u>Buonarroti</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>A company owned by this man inspired the term \"red carpet treatment\" for its</u></b> <b><u>treatment of customers. This man's company operated the Water Level Route and the</u></b> <b><u>High Line, which is now a park. Grand Central Depot was built by this man for his New</u></b> <b><u>York (*)</u> Central Railroad, and this man opposed Daniel Drew's takeover of the Erie Railroad. This man's career began working for steamboat owner Thomas Gibbons of </b><em><b>Gibbons v. Ogden</b></em><b> fame. The original benefactor to a namesake (*) </b>university in Nashville, for ten points, who was this railroad magnate \"Commodore\"?", "answer": "Cornelius <b><u>Vanderbilt</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This country's leader, Johnson Aguiyi-Ironsi [[ah-GWEE-yee-ee-RAHN-see]],</u></b> <b><u>was assassinated in the July Counter Coup, leading to the rule of Yakubu Gowon [[yah-</u><u>KOO-boo goo-WON]]. This country promoted \"Reconciliation, Reconstruction, and</u></b> <b><u>Rehabilitation,\" and its Colonel (+)</u> Olusegun Obasanjo [[oh-LOO-seh-gun oh-BAH-sahn-joh]] declared \"no victor, no vanquished\" during a war against Philip Effiong [[EFF-ee-yong]] and the Republic of (*) </b>Biafra. With a population of mostly Igbo and Yorubas, for ten points, what is this country which moved its capital from Lagos to Abuja?", "answer": "Federal Republic of <b><u>Nigeria</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}